<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The commons complaint VVherein is contained tvvo speciall grieuances: The first, the generall destruction and waste of woods in this kingdome, with a remedy for the same: also how to plant wood according tyo the nature of euery soyle, without losse of any ground; and how thereby many more and better cattel may be yeerely bred, with the charge and profit that yeerely may arise thereby. The second grieuance is, the extreme dearth of victuals. Fovre remedies for the same. ...</title>
            <author>Standish, Arthur, fl. 1611-1613.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1611</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 25 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12915</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23201</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110882</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846343</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846343</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11304</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12915)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11304)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1671:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The commons complaint VVherein is contained tvvo speciall grieuances: The first, the generall destruction and waste of woods in this kingdome, with a remedy for the same: also how to plant wood according tyo the nature of euery soyle, without losse of any ground; and how thereby many more and better cattel may be yeerely bred, with the charge and profit that yeerely may arise thereby. The second grieuance is, the extreme dearth of victuals. Fovre remedies for the same. ...</title>
                  <author>Standish, Arthur, fl. 1611-1613.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 34 p.; folded plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Stansby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1611.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Arthur Standish.</note>
                  <note>Includes folding cut of a fowl house.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Forests and forestry --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Agriculture --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Food supply --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11304:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>THE COMMONS COMPLAINT.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN IS CONTAI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NED TVVO SPECIALL GRIEVANCES:</hi> The firſt, the generall deſtruction and waſte of Woods in this Kingdome, with a remedy for the ſame: Alſo how to plant Wood according to the nature of euery Soyle, without loſſe of any Ground; and how thereby many more and better Cattell may be yeerely bred, with the charge and profit that yeerely may ariſe thereby.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>THE SECOND GRIEVANCE IS, THE EXTREAME DEARTH OF VICTVALS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>FOVRE REMEDIES FOR THE SAME.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> By a generall Planting of Fruit-trees, with the charge and profit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> By an extraordinary breeding of Fowle and Pullen in places conuenient, by a Plot herein ſet downe for the purpoſe, with the charge and profit.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> By a generall deſtroying of all kind of Vermine, with a neere eſtimation what is yeerely deuoured and deſtroyed by them, and how the moſt of them in ſhort time may be deſtroyed with a ſmall charge.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Prouing the abundance of Corne, that is yerely deuoured and deſtroyed by the infinite number of Pidgeons, kept and maintained in this Kingdome.</item>
            </list>
            <p>LONDON <hi>Printed by</hi> William Stansby. <hi>1611.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11304:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11304:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the <hi>KINGS</hi> moſt Excellent <hi>MAIESTIE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>EXT vnto GOD, moſt dread Soueraigne, the loue and dutie that I owe vnto your Maieſtie and Kingdome, hath imbold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me to Dedicate the fruits of my old age and trauell vnto your Highneſſe, hoping that the ſubiect thereof will no way offend You. It is intended to the good of your Maieſtie and your Royall Progenie, the generall good of the Common-wealth for all poſteritie; and in part tendeth to your Princely
<pb facs="tcp:11304:3"/> ſpeech to the Parliament. What I ſhall herein ſet downe I prooue by the beſt Schoolemaſter, which is, my long experience, hauing ſpent many yeares in the attaining thereunto, eſpecially theſe foure laſt yeares, wherein I haue imployed my ſtudy and trauel through ſome parts of moſt of the Countries of this Kingdome for this purpoſe, oft ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing conference with many of the beſt Commonwealths-men for my better vnderſtanding; deſiring by all good means to ataine to a perfect knowledge how to Plant, preſerue, and maintaine the bleſsings of God as well in this our deſtroying age as they haue beene in former times, wherein was left a prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and plentie of that which is now in effect deſtroyed. All are giuen to take the profit preſent, but few or none at all
<pb facs="tcp:11304:3"/> regard the poſteritie or future times. This exerciſe in all ages hath beene in high account with the wiſeſt and moſt worthieſt, and hath beene bleſſed by God himſelfe, (as hath appeared to the world:) and by the approbation of your Maieſtie, may bee ſo put in execution, as the branches thereof may bee ſpread ouer all your Dominions, to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burdening of your louing Subiects of all their grieuances preſent and to come. I ſpare to proceede any further, ſince your Maieſtie whom God hath filled with the ſpirit of wiſedome in vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, by your ready apprehenſion vnderſtandeth much more then I can ſpeake heereof. Thus ſubmitting my poore labours, or rather worthleſſe mite, to the conſideration of your Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Maieſty, hauing nothing elſe to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb facs="tcp:11304:4"/> the ſame withall, but my humble prayers to the King of Kings, to mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply the giftes of his holy Spirit more and more vpon you, and that you may Reigne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny happie yeeres a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Highneſſe moſt humble Subiect,</hi> Arthur Standiſh.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:11304:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hou haſt here gentle Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, brought home vnto thee the harueſt of my long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, with little labour or coſt vnto thy ſelfe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in thou mayeſt plainely according to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of euery Soyle, learne how to plant ſuch profits as naturally our Country hath, and will afoord for the profit of thy ſelfe and Countrey. Firſt, how to plant Wood, and how to breed Cattell to a greater number, yeerely to thy great gaine, as ſhall plainely be proued. Jn the ſecond, the profit of plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting fruit trees in Hedges or Orchards, as of Apples, Wardens and Peares; being no ſtrange nouelties, although by want of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrie
<pb facs="tcp:11304:5"/> they are made ſtrange vnto vs, by our buying them from foraine Countries at a deare rate, by our ſlouth and negligence; whereas by the bleſsing of God, the very ſoyle of our Hedges is ſuch, as they would yeeld great plentie, without hindring any other profit, and may bee gained with leſſe coſt and labour, then any other commoditie in this Kingdome whatſoeuer, as ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in be proued. Jn the third, the maner how to breede Fowle and Pullen, by a ſecure plot from ſtealing, and from vermine. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, how by a ſpeedy meanes to deſtroy all kind of Vermine, eſpecially the feathered kind, with a neere eſtimation what is yere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed by Vermin and Pidgeons, both in Corne and other things. By means there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, not onely Corne, but eſpecially other victuals is brought and doth continue at too deere a rate, for the poore Artificer and Labouring man; by which dearth, too oft
<pb facs="tcp:11304:5"/> ariſeth diſcontents, and mutinies among the common ſort, as appeared of late by a grieuance taken onely of the dearth of Corne, in Warwickeſhire, Northampton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire and other places, about which time the minds of many were moleſted: whereupon J tooke the firſt occaſion to imploy my Studie and trauell in this buſineſſe, hoping by Gods helpe to preuent ſuch inconueniencies, as too oft doth ſpring out of the deſperate tree of want. Whereupon good Reader, it inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that by the obſeruing of theſe ſmall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, thou mayeſt performe ſome part of the cauſe of thy creation, by giuing glorie to thy Creator, honour, pleaſure, and profit to thy King, Countrey, and to thy ſelfe alſo, by feeling and relieuing thy Chriſtian bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wants, and by a charitable industrie, thou mayeſt raiſe meanes to disburthen them of all their grieuances preſent and to
<pb facs="tcp:11304:6"/> come, and in the end, by the mercie of our good God, thou mayeſt bee partaker of his louing promiſes in the Goſpell, <hi>Come you bleſſed of my Father, &amp;c.</hi> The which J craue for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <head>VPON THE AVTHOR AND HIS Moſt commendable and neceſſarie worke.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>FOr me thy paines and ſubiect to commend</l>
               <l>(Each praiſing each by their dumbe ſilence beſt)</l>
               <l>Were candle light vnto the Sunne to lend,</l>
               <l>Send Owles to Athens, paint the Phoenix breſt;</l>
               <l>Giue Flora Garlands, Loue his Myrtle bow,</l>
               <l>Arabia odours, pearle to <hi>Thetis</hi> brow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Loe the Genius of faire Britaine, by</l>
               <l>Commands me ſpeake, and giue thee thy deſert,</l>
               <l>Who art ſo carefull of poſterity,</l>
               <l>And preſent times vnrew'd of greater part:</l>
               <l>Swearing by Thames ſhe's more enritcht by <hi>Standiſh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then all the gold ſhee got by <hi>Drake</hi> and <hi>Candiſh.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <closer>
               <signed>Henry Peacham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:11304:6"/>
            <head>THE COMMONS COMPLAINT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee do in all humbleneſſe complaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your Maieſty of the general deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and waſte of wood made within this your Kingdome, more within twenty or thirty laſt yeares then in any hundred yeares before. Little reſpect is taken but by your Maieſty, for the poſterity and proſperity of your Kingdom: to many deſtroyers, but few or none at al doth plant or preſerue: by reaſon therof there is no Timber left in this Kingdome at this inſtant onely to repaire the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings thereof an other age, much leſſe to build withall: whereby this greeuance doth daily increaſe. The reaſons are many: firſt the want of fire is expected, without the which mans life cannot be preſerued: ſecondly, the want of Timber, Bricke, Tile, Lime, Iron, Lead and Glaſſe for the building of habitations. Timber for the maintaining of husbandry, for nauigation, for veſſels, for bruing and the keeping of drinke, and all other neceſſaries for houſe-keeping: barke for the tanning of Leather, bridges for tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, pales for Parkes, poles for Hoppes, and ſalt from the Wiches. The want of wood is, and will be a great decay
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:11304:7"/> to tillage, and cannot but bee the greateſt cauſe of the dearth of corne, and hindreth greatly the yearely breeding of many cattell, by reaſon that much ſtraw is yearely bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that to the breeding of cattell might bee imployed: the want of wood in many places of this Kingdome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraineth the foyll of cattell to be burned, which ſhould be imployed to the ſtrengthning of land, and ſo doth the want of hurdels for the folding of ſheepe, and the want of wood cauſeth too many great loſſes by fire, that commeth by the burning of ſtraw, and ſo it may be conceiued, no wood no Kingdome.</p>
            <div type="remedies">
               <head>The remedies may be thus.</head>
               <p>IF that all owners of land according to the nature of the ſoiles wherein there lands doe lie, were enioyned to plant all their hedges with wood (and not onely with thornes) ſo thicke as conueniently trees may grow and proſper, allowing foure yardes betweene tree and tree: to be topped and lopped for fire-wood (reſeruing ſome part of their hedges where they may thinke it moſt coueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent for their profite, to bee planted with fruit trees, or to plant all with fire-wood, and plant fruit trees in Orchards, according to their beſt liking). And that they might bee further enioyned to plant for euery acre in their ſeuerall occupations, foure trees more, to be preſerued for Timber for ſo many yeares before any of them ſhould bee felled, as the trees may be growne to be good Timber, which will be neere foureſcore yeares: and that after that the trees bee growne to be Timber, that none ſhould be felled, or at any time before or after waſted, but ſo many to be planted and continued: And that all ſuch perſons as haue at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:11304:7"/> their grounds furniſhed with wood, in ſuch ſort as is required, might bee alſo enioyned hereafter to plant and preſerue ſo many trees and ſo much wood, as heareafter they ſhall fell or waſte. And that all tenants might be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned in like ſort to plant their hedges with trees for fire, and to haue the lops to their owne houſes for fire, and to plant two trees for euery acre in their occupations for Tymber. This being performed, no wit can comprehend what good may in time grow thereby vnto the Kingdome, although ſome taſt may be taken by the planting of twenty acres as followeth, with other directions for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. And for the better conceiuing thereof: admit that a man haue twenty acres onely in his occupation of paſture ground, wherein hee yearely breedeth or feedeth twentie cattell, and that hee ſhould for this purpoſe in cloſe in the drieſt corner of that cloſe halfe an acre, and that there were no fence before about the ſame, but that it were to be incloſed round with a good ditch and hedge, which would containe forty eight Rode, and that the charge at the firſt ſhould coſt three pound ſixe ſhillings eight pence, and that the maintayning thereof, till the wood that is therein to be planted ſhould bee paſt taking hurt by cattell, which may be ten yeares, ſhould coſt two pound thirteene ſhillings foure pence more, being in all ſixe pound, more by the halfe then it can coſt. The halfe acre being thus incloſed, digge therein about Chriſtmas ſeuen ſcore and tenne plots of a yard ſquare, leauing three yardes euery way betweene the plots digged; let it lie with the graſſe ſide downe till about Midſomer, then digge it againe: and againe abut Hollan-tyde, when the Maſt of Okes, Beech, or the Chates of Aſh falleth from the trees: then take of the ſame Maſt or Chates, according to the nature of the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:11304:8"/> ſoile, and ſet them halfe a foote a ſunder, and not aboue a hand bredth deepe, and keepe it weeded well the firſt two yeares; being ſure that the ſpring be not troden on: after which time there may be in September about the middeſt thereof, the ſappe being then in the roote, all the young plants drawne vp to be planted in the hedges of the ſame cloſe, onely reſeruing two in euery plot of the beſt, being moſt likely to be trees, and after ſixe yeares there may be drawne vp halfe the reſt to be planted elſe where, leauing then onely a hundred and fiftie: in which time the ground may be mowed betweene the plants, ſo that thereby there is ſmall loſſe: for after the three firſt yeares the ground may be eaten with ſheepe, and after ten yeares the ground may be laid forth to the cloſe, as it was before with ſeuen ſcore and ten yong trees, which within foureſcore yeares may well be worth ſo many pounds. The hedges being planted as is ſet downe cannot yeeld ſo little fire-wood as may be worth twenty ſhillings a yeare: the twenty cattell that there is to bee bred or fedde cannot bee leſſe bettered then two ſhillings in a beaſt yearely by their quiet liuing in the wood thus planted: keeping there the fleſh that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they loſt: being before conſtrained by the extreme heate of the Sunne, and Flyes, for want of ſhadow or wormeſtall, to runne vp and downe the cloſe looſing the fleſh in the heat that they got in the coole, and ſo ſpoyling the water with running into it, as ſeldome they could get their bellies full of water (the want thereof breedeth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſeaſes.) And further by the quiet being of the cattell in the wood, there is graſſe ſaued yearely worth twenty ſhilings, which before was ſpoyled by the cattels running, treading and foyling of the graſſe. And by this meanes it appeareth, that after ten yeares the twenty acres may be
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:11304:8"/> improued at the leaſt fortie ſhillings a yeare by the cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell: ſo that it is but three yeares profite thus to improue the twenty acres. And this for the breeding and feeding of cattell, all breeders and feeders will affirme, and that a better breed of cattell may be raiſed of thoſe grounds that wanteth good water for their cattell and ſhadow: and for thoſe grounds that wantes either, can neuer breed good cattell, or make ſo much profite of their Dairies, as beſt may appeare betweene Lancaſhire and Lincolnſhire, and al other countries where ſuch meanes of water and wood is wanting. And by the wood the twenty acres is bettered at the leaſt other fortie ſhillings a yeare: for if it be caſt it ſhall apeare, that a tree growing till it be foureſcore years olde, being then worth twenty ſhillings, it groweth after three pence a yeare. So that ſo many timber-trees ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny pounds beſides the fire-wood. What loſſe or gaine here is required, I leaue to be cenſured by the Reader.</p>
               <div type="objections">
                  <head>OBIECTIONS.</head>
                  <p>It hath beene obiected that it is againſt a mans profite to preſerue his woods, for they grow but at three ſhillings foure pence an acre <hi>per annum,</hi> &amp; the ground being conuerted to paſture it is worth tenne ſhillings an acre <hi>per annum.</hi> And further it hath been ſaid by ſome that they haue wood enough for them &amp; their heires, let them plant wood that needeth, either for building or any other vſes: and that it cannot bee conceiued how wood can bee planted, in reſpect of the difference of ſoiles, or how plants may be gotten to plant the Kingdome withall, or that any ſuch profite may ariſe, and that there is Sea cooles enow to ſupply many wants,</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:11304:9"/>
                  <head>THE ANSVVER.</head>
                  <p>THe Obiections are too true, as may appeare to the world as touching wood, but not in the reſt, as hath beene proued, and might further appeare if a ſuruay were taken of the woodes now growing in this Kingdome: for it would bee found that the fourth part is not able to maintaine it ſelfe threeſcore yeares without good maintayning and preſeruing. And as touching the difference of ſoile, who knoweth not, may heereby know, that wood hath and will grow in moſt part of all this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, being planted and preſerued, as firſt appeareth by the peakes of Darby ſhiere and other ſtonie countries, where there is yet to bee ſeene Aſhe woode growing about euery towne, though very rockie: as for Oke, Beech, Elme, and Aſhe, it doth grow in flinty or grauelly ground, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by the Chilterne Country, (as it is termed in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhieres) and on the grauelly grounds euery way about London, by Elme: and for ſoft fenniſh groundes, it appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth about the townes that there is ſome, and hath beene better ſtore of Elme and Willow, and other ſuch like woods, and would bee if it were planted and preſerued. The maner how to plant elme &amp; Willow, is to lop a yong elme or Willow, the lop beeing but of three yeares growth, in the latter end of March or the beginning of Aprill, when the ſappe is vp in the boughes, and the buddes ready to put foorth: then cutte off the boughes ſo lopped, cut them in lengthes of a foote long Coult-foote wiſe, leauing the knot where the budde is to bee put forth in the middeſt; then lay theſe ſhort boughes in trenches where you would haue the wood to grow, three or foure fingers deepe, and couer
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:11304:9"/> them well with mould well troden, leauing the knot bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in moyſt ground for the Willow, the Elme will growe in harder ground: If the Spring bee drie then water them, and aſſuredly they will grow ſooner to bee Trees then ſets, ſo will the bough of any Tree, as well of fruit trees as others, and the talleſt and ſtraighteſt of the ſame being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Lammas, and as neere the body of the Tree as may be; with a Knife cut the Barke of the bough cleane a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way of a hand breadth, leauing not any Barke for the ſappe to returne withall to the body, the Barke being thus taken away, then immediatly take a good quantitie of Clay, and lay thereon ſome good earth of the ſide that is to bee layed next the tree: and lap the ſaid Claye and Earth about the bough, vpon the Barke next to the place where the Barke is taken off, a hand breadth at the leaſt, and moſſe it and bind it as a graft, ſo let it ſtand till the midſt of September, then ſawe it off and ſet it were you would haue it to grow, and as neere as you can with the ſame ſide to the Sunne as was before, and aſſuredly they will grow to be trees for to be lopped for fire, and your fruit trees will ſome of them beare fruit the firſt yeere, but the ſecond certainely, if the yeere be ſeaſonable. And ſo will litle yong roots of Elme being taken when the ſappe is in them, and ſet as quick ſets, by which meanes the Fenniſh countries may haue Elme, Timber fire-wood, and wormeſtall or ſhelter for their cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell. And as for Sea-coales, there is no aſſurance how long they may indure: it is apparant that Coale mines doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay too faſt in moſt Countryes, and are too chargeable to many Countryes in reſpect of carriage, and in moſt mines are not to be got without the vſe of much wood.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="benefits">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:11304:10"/>
                  <head>What further benefite may be made on ſheepe-walkes, Downes or Heathes, by planting of wood where the grounds are barren.</head>
                  <p>IF for example, that on euery Sheepe-walke whereon there is or may be kept fiue hundred ſheepe, there were plowed vp about Chriſtmas twenty acres in the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt bottom of the walke for this purpoſe, where water may be kept all the yeare, aſwell for the breeding of Fowle, as for the other profites: all which may be maintained vnder one charge by the Shepheard (without fencing, for that on ſuch Downes little cattell commeth.) Being ſo plowed, let it lie till Midſomer: if then it be perceiued that there will be Maſt that yeare, then plough it againe, and then let it lie vntill about Hallowmas: Then take the Maſt of Oke, Beech and the Chats of Aſhe, bruſed Crabbs, after the veriuice is preſſed out, and hawes: mingle theſe together to ſow about the ſides and endes of the ground about a yard broad, and vpon the reſt ſow no hawes, but ſome few kernels of Crabs, then begin at a ſide and ſow fiue yards of bredth, &amp; plough vnder this Maſt and Chats very ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, then leaue ſixe yardes in breadth, and ſow and plough fiue yardes more, and ſo from ſide to ſide. And bee ſure to leaue a yard and halfe at the laſt ſide The reſt of the head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands to lie till the reſt of the Cloſe bee ſowen in March with Otes, that the cattell may not hurte the Maſt ſowen by treading on it.</p>
                  <p>The cloſe being thus ſowen with Maſt and Otes, in the meane time there would be a houſe builded for the ſhep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard to dwell in, where he may beſt ouerſee the ground for his eaſe. The charge thereof, firſt, of the houſe fiue pound, the plowing thrice and the harrowing two ſhillings
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:11304:10"/> eight pence an acre, eight pound the Maſt, and getting it readie fortie ſhillings, for fiue quarters of Otes to ſow the ground fiftie ſhillings: for the getting of Otes in harueſt, and carrying of them into the barne fiftie ſhillings, and ſo the whole charge is twenty pound, whereof the Otes will yeeld fifteene pound, if they increaſe but ſix of one. Then when the ſpring is of two yeares growth, there may be drawne vp part of the ſpring, which may be imploied for quickſets, &amp; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the remainder is ſix years of growth there may be more drawne vp to be ſet: at which drawing there may be got as many as will bee well worth fiue pound, lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing then none but forty foure of eyther ſide of euery row, fiue yards betweene euery one, and here and there to leaue ſome ſpeciall one that is like to bee a fine tree for Tymber, and ſome hundred or more of the Crab-tree ſtockes to graft on, and in the hedge rounde about to bee left thicke foure yardes betweene euery tree, and ſo leaue as there may be left at the leaſt three thouſand fiue hundred beſides Crab-trees. Theſe three thouſand fiue hundred growing twenty yeares, there may bee then two thouſand ſtocked vp, which will bee well worth twelue pence a piece to bee ſold, fiue hundred of the very beſt to remaine for Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber trees, and a thouſand to be topped, which at euery ten yeares end may bee lopped for fire wood: the tops of that thouſand trees cannot be ſo little worth as fifty pound: by which meanes at that twenty yeares end there may be gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the two thouſand trees that are ſtocked, a hundred pound, and fiue hundred trees left, that within foureſcore yeares may well bee worth fiue hundred pound: the thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand trees remayning to bee lopped will grow after fiue pound <hi>per annum</hi> at the leaſt, and the ground being before barren (hardly worth twelue pence an acre) will be worth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:11304:11"/> ten ſhillings an acre <hi>per annum:</hi> for by the graſſe and weeds that will grow the firſt ſixe yeares, and the lodging of the ſheepe in the night, when the weather is ſuch as they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be folded, and the ſhaddow of the trees, which are ſo to bee planted that there may bee eleuen yards betweene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery tre, except in the hedges. The ground will be made very good meddow, and will finde the ſheepe hay enough with good winter paſture, and warme ſhelter in ſharpe weather. And if water can be kept, there may be bred with twenty pound coſt, fowle or pullen well worth twenty nobles <hi>per annum,</hi> all charges borne,: if the plot for fowle, be neare corne, then may there bee beſt kept wilde Duckes and Mallards, which doe neuer hurt corne in field.</p>
                  <p>If thc like planting of wood were on common Sheepe-walks, Common paſtures, and Commons where the lands are ſo good as they might be ſowen with Wheate or Rye, with the maſt, the whole charge thereof would be made in three yeares with twenty pound gained at the leaſt, by the croppe of Wheate or Rye, and a crop of Otes after be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the grounds where the Maſt is ſowne, as before is ſet downe. If the like prouiſion were made in Parkes where wood decayeth, and hay is ſcant for Deere, it would bee very beneficiall to the owners, and by the planting our Commons, common paſtures, or common Sheepe-walks by the charges of the towne whereunto ſuch grounds doe belong, the charge will be inned, as before is ſet downe, in three yeares a preſent reliefe rayſed by fowle to the poore of the towne, of ſix pound thirteene ſhillings foure pence, and after ten yeares, three pound ſixe ſhillings eight pence at the leaſt by fruite: after twenty yeares by two thouſand trees that may be ſtocked, one hundred pound to remaine for a ſtocke, and fiue hundred trees, to bee left for
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:11304:11"/> Timber, and one thouſand trees remayning to be lopped which may yeelde woode worth fiue pound a yeare; by which meanes the townes where ſuch prouiſion may bee made, may not onely be greatly eaſed of the charge of their poore, but alſo haue a ſtock whereby they may be alwaies diſcharged of ſuch charges as may happen eyther to Church or King by the increaſe of the ſtocke. And further take certaine knowledg that all barren and moſſie grounds may be improued much by letting three yeares graſſe rot on the ground, and it is the onely way next vnto lime to deſtroy Moſſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="grievance">
               <head>The ſecond grieuance, is the dearth of Victuals, with remedy for the ſame.</head>
               <p>COncerning Victuals, the want thereof is very great, in regard that all kind of Victuals is riſen and growen more deere in price within theſe laſt ſixe yeeres then in twentie yeeres before: And if the dearth of Victuals ſhall ſo happen to increaſe but a fewe yeeres to come (as by all likelyhoode it is like for to doe) except ſome ſpeedy remedy be prouided, the poore man by his labours ſhall not get wherewith to relieue himſelfe and family. This dearth may bee much eaſed, if that euery one that hath a Pigeon houſe might bee enioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or otherwiſe required to breed yearely extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily a certaine number of fowle or pullen, as ſhall ſeeme beſt to their liking. The manner and faſhion ſhall be ſet downe by a plot for the purpoſe, how they may be bred, with the charge and profite that may yearely ariſe to the owners.</p>
               <p>The reaſons whereof are fiue: firſt, in regard that a plot
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:11304:12"/> to breed fowle or pullen in, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> may be made &amp; furniſhed with leſſe charges then a Pigeon houſe, yeeldeth more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite, and nothing at all offendeth the people; wheras the Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons are a great cauſe of this dearth, and more chargeable then profitable to their owners, and the loſſe that the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom receiueth thereby is infinit, as at large ſhall be proued.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that it is to be ſuppoſed that euery one that is able to build a Pigeon houſe, is alſo able to make a plot for fowle or pullen to breed in, and eyther is or ſhould be the Lord of the Mannor, who hath to his Mannor ſome conuenient ground to make a plot on for that purpoſe, and to breed ſo many pullen or fowle yearly as he keepeth Pigeons.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that as a Pigeon houſe is builded for houſe-kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, ſo the fowle and pullen is more profitable, as alſo ſhall be proued.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, that as the extreme dearth of victuals cauſeth many to breake vp houſ-keeping, and to put away their ſeruants, whereby many through want fall to ſtealing, and therby come to an vntimely end: ſo an extraordinary bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of fowle and pullen, with other meanes as followeth, may by Gods bleſſing ſo eaſe the extremitie thereof, as men may, as their aunceſtors haue in former ages, delight in hoſpitality, and thereby preuent many inconueniences that the extremity of dearth doth and may procure.</p>
               <p>Fiftly and laſtly, the profite of the Fowle and pullen ſhal be proued to bee ſuch as no charitable Chriſtian can denie to performe.</p>
               <p>Now to proue the difference of the charge and profite betweene a Pigeon houſe and a plot for fowle and pullen: Firſt, all men of experience know that an ordinary Pigeon houſe of fiue yardes and a halfe ſquare, and foure yardes
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:11304:12"/> high to the eueſings; in which houſe there may bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained twelueſcore paire of Pigeons, will coſt fiue and twenty pound at the leaſt, and that it will be three yeares before it commeth to the beſt profite: and when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to that, the beſt Pigeon houſe is ſeldome worth fiue pound <hi>per annum,</hi> except it bee within threeſcore miles of London, where all victuals are dearer then in other places of the Kingdome, or a double houſe. I will not ſtand to proue the opinion of the multitude, of the charge of a Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, that ſhe will eate (if ſhe haue liberty) a quarter of corne in a yeare (although I haue ſome reaſon to beleeue it, for that two credible perſons did affirme vnto me, that they had lately ſeene halfe a pinte of corne at one time, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of an old Pigeons crop, and offered to make proofe thereof by witneſſes of good credite:) but I will admit of that which in common reaſon is not to be deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that Pigeons haue corne at will to feede on more then halfe the yeare: and admitting that there bee twelueſcore paire in a houſe of olde Pigeons, as commonly there is, and that euery olde pigeon in that time with her young ones ſhould eate but two buſhels, which commeth to ſixe ſcore quarters at a houſe: &amp; it is generally holden that they hinder the increaſe of that which would grow, and ſpoyle as much as they eate, from the time that corne groweth ripe in the fielde, before harueſt bee done and the ſeede times. And thus in reaſon it doth appeare, that in all the ſeed times of the yeare there is at the leaſt ſixteene weekes, in which time ſhe gathereth vp much corne that is leaſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered by the harrowes, which a ſhower of raine would couer, and ſo would growe: and naturally all Peaſe and Beanes if they fall not deepe in ſowing, and bee very well couered, they will ſwell out of the ground, and lie bare vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:11304:13"/> the ground: and yet not withſtanding Peaſe and Beanes, and all other corne by nature groweth with the root firſt into the ground, and then ſpingeth vpwards: ſo that after the ſeede times bee done, and the corne groweth greene, till it gtow ſo high that the Pigeons cannot goe through it, they gather vp the corne growing, and breake off the blades, and eate the corne: all which will be confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently proued by all Husbandmen and Gentlemen, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially by ſuch as ſometimes lend their minds to vnderſtand the profite of husbandry.</p>
               <p>This being allowed (which by no meanes can be diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued) it appeareth that twelue ſcore paire of Pigeons de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure, deſtroy and hinder the increaſe of twelue ſcore quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of corne in a yeare. Admit it were but halfe ſo much, and that the corne were rated, being Wheat, Rye, Barley and Peaſe, but at two ſhillinges and a penny the buſhell, ſixeſcore quarters commeth to a hundred pound <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> at a houſe. Admit further, that the ſixt part thereof be the owners of the Pigeon houſe (for ſo it is to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that the Lord of the Mannor hath a ſixth part of the towne, then it followeth that his fiue pounds-worth of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons coſteth him ſixteene pound thirteene ſhillings and eight pence at the leaſt. What other charge his Pigeons are vnto him, I forbeare to relate: the number of the Pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on houſes cannot be fewer then forty thouſand, with the Pigeons kept at houſes. Now to the charge and profite of fowle or pullen: the plot and all things thereunto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will not coſt aboue twenty pound, to haue it ſecure, and ſo as when occaſion is, that ſome of the wilde kinde is taken, the taking of ſome may not offend the reſt that are to remaine. The plot muſt be eſpecially for the wilde kinde of Duck and Mallard, which are beſt to be kept both
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:11304:13"/> for profite and pleaſure, in a piece of ground where water is and may be got and kept al the yeare, of two and twenty yards ſquare, to be moted about with a mote of a rode or pole of bredth, which wil be twenty pole about; to be made ſixe foot deepe in the middeſt, and ſomething ſhallower towards the ſides, which will coſt at fiue ſhillings a rode, fiue pound. The leuelling of the ground, with quickſet and workemanſhip, foure pound, the houſe being fiue yardes ſquare and ſixe foot high, and hauing a little chamber ouer it to keepe Otes in to feed them: the houſe to be but ſtud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and thinly lathed, two fingers betweene the lathes: which houſe cannot coſt aboue eight pound, and the bridge and doore twenty ſhillings.</p>
               <p>The plot being made, put into it about Chriſtmas three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore tame Duckes and twenty Mallards, which will coſt about three and fifty ſhillings foure pence, or at Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas for want of Duckes, fortie Hennes and ten Cocks, to remaine till wilde Ducke egges be gotten to breede on in the meane time: there are neither the Hennes nor the Duckes, but their egges will be worth the corne, branne, and draines that the yong Ducklings muſt be fedde with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, till they can eate Oates. The plot being thus ready and all things elſe, ſend one with a horſe for egges in March in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Cambridge-ſhiere into the fennes, or into any other neerer place, where wilde duckes egges are to be got for money, eſpecially in the fennes, if the people haue liberty to get them (for in the ſpring time when the wilde duckes laye, the poore ſort will goe with a dogge into the fennes, where their dog wil put vp the fowle out off their neaſts, and then if they finde many egges therein that be vnſitten, they will take moſt of them away with a ladle, or by ſome other meanes; ſo that they neither handle the egges that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:11304:14"/> they leaue behinde, nor breathe vpon them; and then will marke the place where the neſt is, ſo as they may readily come to it, and once in a weeke wil fetch all the egges that are laide in the meane time, and ſo make the ducke (whoſe nature is to lay till her neaſt be full before ſhe will ſitte) ſo poore as they may take her (which oftentimes the hungry ſort do.) The egges being thus got ready, when the keeper of them ſeeth the hen or duck feather her neaſt, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to ſit, then lay in the neaſt twelue wilde ducke egges. And thus in two yeares the whole number of the wilde or tame may be bred in ſuch ſort as they may be taken off at the owners pleaſure, and a ſtocke of foure-ſcore of the ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt to be left for breeding with twenty Mallards: which foure ſcore olde duckes will breed and bring vp common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly euery one of them eight at the leaſt; the whole number to bee three hundred and twenty couple, to be ſolde, are well worth eight pence the couple, which ariſeth to the ſumme of ten pound, and a marke for their young ones. Then the egges that they will yearely lay to be but worth fifty three ſhillings and foure pence, at fiue a penny; and the Fiſh thar may bee bred in the Mote yearely, to bee worth thirteene ſhillings foure pence: prouided alwayes that there breede no Pikes, for they will deſtroy the yong Fowle but not the Pullen. The whole Summe is fourteene pound, deduct out of the ſame fiue pound, to buy tenne quarters of Oates yearely, which ten quarters will allow the Fowles aboue a buſhell and halfe a weeke, which is more then is needfull to be ſpent on them: for except it be in Froſt or Snow when the ground is couered, or when they ſitte, and the young ones are not able to flye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, a very ſmall quantity will ſerue to giue them euery morning a few, that euery one may get a dozen cornes.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:11304:14"/> As for their breede, being once well haunted, they will neuer away in the day, if they may be in quiet, but altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the night, by which meanes they are ſafe from Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, and they will continue there eſpecially in breeding time. For experience teacheth all men to know, that all thing that hath life, loueth beſt the place wherein it was bred, finding there their beſt reliefe and reſt: as appeareth that all the Winter (till breeding time) there are hardly one couple of Duckes and Mallards to be ſeene in the Fennes, but abundance in Summer time, where they remaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til about Michaelmas, and then they go away againe. Then further allow forty ſixe ſhillings eight pence to the keepers and towards the keeping of the Hedge, the remainder is cleere (all charges defrayed) ſixe pound thirteene ſhillings and foure pence. Thus is the proofe made betweene the Pigeons and the wilde Fowle.</p>
               <p>The plot for tame will not coſt ſo much by the charge of the houſe for being tame, they may be taken at pleaſure.</p>
               <p>The Pullen will yeeld a greater profite: for there may be likewiſe kept at a like plot, foureſcore Hennes, and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Cockes, admit euery Hen to breed yearely but eight Chickens, (though it will bee graunted they will breede twiſe in euery yeare, and at each time eight at the leaſt) their number is ſixteeneſcore couple, whereof eightſcore couple to bee ſold being Chickens at ſixpence the couple, make foure pound. Foureſcore couple of Hennes at twelue pence the couple comes to foure pound, and foureſcore couple of Capons at two ſhillings the couple, comes to eight pound. The Egges cannot bee leſſe worth then eight pound at fiue a penny. And the fiſh that may be bred yearely in the Mote will yeeld thirteene ſhillinges foure pence: The totall is twenty foure pound, thirteene ſhil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:11304:15"/> and foure pence, out of which deduct thirteene pound, to buy twentie ſixe quarters of Oates, whereby they may be allowed one weeke with another throughout the yeare, foure buſhels. Allow further yearely foure pound to the keeper of the Pullen and the maintaining of the plot, although it be ſuppoſed, that euery one that will bee at the charge of any of theſe Plots, keepeth one that tendeth his Pullen that he hath already, ſo that the charge hereof will bee ſo much the leſſe. The houſe for Pullen will coſt about fortie ſhillings more then a houſe for Fowle, in reſpect that although the houſe may bee two yardes narrower, yet it muſt be three yardes longer, with Poles in it for the Pullen to ſit vpon. As for neſts they ſhal neede none in the houſe, but in borders where they will take more delight to breede in then in a houſe, and bee freer from diſeaſes, by reaſon of the ayre, therefore it ſhall not bee greatly needeful to haue a Chamber in that houſe, for that the Keeper may bring the Oates at any time when hee commeth to them. But the reaſon why a Chamber is conuenient in the houſe, wherein the Fowle muſt bee vſed to feede, is eſpecially for the Keeper to ſtay priuately in to take ſome of the Fowle at pleaſure, without offending the reſt. Thus all charges to the vttermoſt being ſet down, the remainder is ſeuen pound thirteene ſhillings and foure pence per andum de claro, at the leaſt at a chepe rate. The charge of the Plot is vnder three yeares purchaſe for the Pullen, and three yeares purchaſe for Duckes and Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lards. As for the manner of breeding of Pullen and tame Fowle, it is needleſſe to ſet downe, onely thus much: For the tame, their charge will be as litle or leſſe then the wild, if they be bred in large Paſtures, where they may neither doe hurt to Corne nor Meadow ground, which the wilde
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:11304:15"/> will neuer doe. The reaſon is, the wild keepe in the water all the day, and feede altogether in the night, and dare not come neere Corne: and their Corne muſt bee giuen them euery morning a little, to drawe them to their bree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding place in the day, whither they will not faile to come, being there bred and fed. It ſhal not be needfull to beſtow much Corne vpon the tame, but onely at their firſt being put into the Plot, where they muſt bee kept in for three weekes or a moneth, in which time being fed euery Eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, they will likewiſe ſo know their being, that thither they will come in the night, and feede abroad all day, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if they find that they ſit quiet in the night; ſuch is the difference of their kinds, the one feedeth by day, and the other by night. Now it remaineth to know how the wild muſt bee bred, when they haue choſen their Neſtes, which ſhall appeare in the Plot hereafter ſet downe.</p>
               <p>After the Fowle begin to lay, once a weeke their Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per may come to their neſtes when the Fowles are off, which will be towards night; and for that purpoſe bring with them an Iron ladle, with a handle halfe a yard long at the leaſt, wherewith they may reach into the neſts of the Fowle, and from thence take ſome of the eldeſt laid Egges, as neere as they can geſſe, leauing not aboue or vnder, two or three; taking great heede that they neither handle them, nor breath vpon them, for their nature is to find that fault, and then they wil forſake their neſts. Thus may the Egges for the more profit be taken from them, ſo long as in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion ſhall be thought fit, which commonly will bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome ten weeks, ere that they be perceiued to feather their neſt: and bee ſure in the meane time to keepe ſome Egges, that had beene neither handled nor breached on, and if there want Egges in any of the neſts, when it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:11304:16"/> that they ſit, then with the Ladle put in more, and make the number twelue at the leaſt. The maner how to take them is thus.</p>
               <p>The houſe being made, as before is ſet down, the doore thereof muſt be thus made: A light frame of Wood as can be made, to be as broad and ſo long as the Doore ſtead is, being for the purpoſe a yard or thereabout, for that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly is the breadth of Canuis or haire Cloth. Then take (for the better laſting) ſo much haire Cloth as the Doore is of height, and make it faſt to the frame of wood as a Doore, which muſt be hanged like a Shop window at the top of the Doore ſtead, to be drawen vp by a Cord and a Pully, and ſo to ſtand. In the meane time the fowle muſt be vſed to be fed in the houſe, which by little and litle they will eaſily be brought vnto, if they be vſually fed there, and ſome tame ones kept among them for that purpoſe, which for ſundry cauſes I hold the fitter to breede on; eſpecially they being not able to flie, muſt of neceſſitie ſtay there, which will make the Duckes to reſort thither for their mates. And ſome doe hold that the nature of the wilde Mallard, is to ſucke the Egges if hee find them; being thus vſed to haue their Corne in the houſe, which they may be brought vnto, whereof I could giue many inſtances, but one may ſerue for breuity: One at S. <hi>Iames,</hi> the other at the houſe from whence I deſcended, the laſt owner thereof had by a Tenant of his a dozen wild Ducke Egges brought him, which he cauſed to bee ſet vnder a Henne, which brought him vp twelue yong Duckes, and of them were bred many about the Mote of his houſe, ſo that there hath beene threeſcore at a time; which although they were wild bred, yet would they haue followed from the Mote through the Court, and into the Hall for meate, being cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="instructions">
                     <body>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11304:17"/>
                        <p>IN the caſting of the Mote, the beſt carth muſt bee cast into the Plot, to raiſe it ſo as the Houſe may ſtand three or foure yards higher then the ſides to the Moteward, that the water may deſcend; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> pleaſure, there may be ſome kind of Quick-wood ſet about it, whereby it may be kept Fort-like. The borders for pleaſure may be ſet with Preuet, whereon many conceites may be faſhioned, ſeeming as though the Fowle bred vnder them; but for profit with Gooſe-berie ſets, which will put forth and be greene time<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly in the yeare, to ſhadow the Neſts. The paſſadges betwene the neſts, would be a yard broad at the leaſt, and in the vaſt places about the houſe, ſome fruit trees may be planted for profit. On the out ſide of the Mote for Fowle, there muſt be a double Quick-wood ſet of Whitethorne, kept thicke in the botome that the Fowle may not creepe through, to be kept battled if the owner pleaſe. The Quick-wood to be ſet cloſe to the ſide of the Bridge, and the Bridge to lie longer forth then the Hedge, by a yard and a halfe, ſo that vnder either ſide of the Bridge, there may be a little Doore to open and ſhut at pleaſure, to the end the wild king after they be fourteene dayes old, may be let forth a nights to feede, and to come in a mornings (whereof they will not faile.) The tame kind muſt not be let forth, till they be paſt taking hurt by Vermine, and they to be let forth a mornings, and to come in a Euenings. For Pullen there needeth no Fence at all on the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide: On the Bridge there muſt be a Doore, and ſo made as no Vermine may creepe in, either ouer or by it, and a Trap continually would be kept on the Bridge. On either ſide the Mote, there muſt be left a yard and a halfe, or rather two yards in the inſide for the Fowle to ſit on at pleaſure, and for fiſhing the Mote, the Mote may be broder at the owners pleaſure. In large Parkes or Paſture grounds, it were moſt profit to be both Fowle and Pullen, the Plats being as farre aſunder as may be.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Place this betweene Fol. 20. and 21.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="diagram">
                     <body>
                        <pb facs="tcp:11304:17"/>
                        <p>
                           <figure>
                              <head>The Figure of the Plot.</head>
                           </figure>
                        </p>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
                  <pb facs="tcp:11304:18"/>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:11304:18"/> and but ſometime vſed ſo for pleaſure. And when it pleaſed the owner to ſee a flight, they were alwayes put out of the Mote, and then would they flie to the riuer, or to ſome other pits of water where they were to be found, and being fline at, as many as eſcaped with life, would not faile to come home. The Fowle being thus wonted to the houſe, the Keeper being determined to take any of them, may goe into the houſe and call them thither, according to his wonted manner, the Corne being ſtrewed in the houſe, the Keeper may goe vp a Ladder into the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and there ſtay with the cord of the Doore in his hand, as priuately as he can, and by degrees let the doore downe, and when hee perceiueth that moſt of the Fowle are gone forth, then may he let the Doore cloſe downe, and ſo take them as quietly as may be, and no whit offend the reſt. If all Noble men and others of the better ſort would put this in execution in Forreſts, Chaſes, Parkes, great Paſtures and Commons, it would not only be very beneficiall for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in their houſe-keeping, but would likewiſe eaſe the extreme dearth of victuals, to the eaſing of this grieuance.</p>
               <div type="objections">
                  <head>Obiections againſt breeding of Fowle.</head>
                  <p>THat ſuch abundance of Fowle by this means may bee bred, that thereby Corne may be made deere. Secondly, that they will deſtroy the increaſe of Fiſh. Thirdly, that they will ſo foyle the ground where they are bred, that the cattell will not eate the graſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The Anſwer to this Obiection.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, as touching the dearth of Corne that by them may grow, that ſhall bee anſwered hereafter in place for that purpoſe, and how more Corne may bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:11304:19"/> by the tenth part then they can ſpend, which is yeare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroyed by Vermine.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that they doe not deſtroy or hinder the breede of Fiſh, as it doth appeare, eſpecially in the Fennes of the Ile of Ely, where there is greater ſtore of Fiſh, then there is in any place of England, except it bee in ſuch like Fennie grounds: in which Ile there is more Fowle then there is in all England beſides, eſpecially in ſpawning time at which time they may doe moſt hurt, but at other times they can doe none: For after there is life in the Fiſh, no ſwimming Fowle can hurt them. And for the better ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of all men in this point, let euery man call to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance whether euer he ſaw or heard of a Fiſh taken out of a wild Mallards crop.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, as touching their foyling of the ground, an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance may be taken by all Fenniſh Commons where they haunt, and by all other Commons where great ſtore of Geeſe are bred and kept, where is to be ſeene the foyle of the Geeſe to be thicke on the ground (and yet the Cattell feeding among it) that in common reaſon they cannot but gather ſome of it into their mouthes: though the foyle of Geeſe is holden the moſt dangerous foile of all other Fowle, yet did I neuer heare any complaine of any loſſe taken either by their foyle or feathers, although in the moulting time, the Commons will ſeeme as it were ſtrowed with feathers. And it is holden by many good Husbands, that Fowles, eſpecially Duckes and Mallards doe much good to ground and Cattel, eſpecially to Deere and Sheepe, namely by gathering vp the Wormes that ſo ſproute vp the earth in the night, which earth in grounds that are eaten bare, is beaten abroad with euery ſhowre of Raine vpon the ſhort graſſe, which commonly is the ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:11304:19"/> whereon the Deere and Sheepe deſire moſt to feede; and thereby gather vp the earth that is ſo beaten on the Graſſe by the raine, which earth is holden by moſt skilfull men in ſheepe, to bee the principall cauſe of the Rotte: which the better may bee conceiued for as much as ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience hath manifeſted, that ſeldome either Sheepe or Deere rotte in grounds deepe of Graſſe. Alſo Wormes liue by the fat of the earth, and decay the ſtrength thereof, (as all the great Gardiners doe affirme) which Fowle and Pullen will deſtroy, eſpecially wild Ducke and Mallard, in reſpect that they altogether feede by night on the bareſt grounds, and vpon Wormes moſt of all.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="remedy">
               <head>The ſecond remedie for the dearth of Victuals, by planting of Fruite.</head>
               <p>FOr as much as by the experience that is taken out of moſt of the Countries of this Kingdome, eſpecially out of ſome parts of Worceſterſhire, Gloceſterſhire, &amp; Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fordſhire, wher it is generally affirmed that there be ſundry men, that raiſeth to their purſes yearly two hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred pounds, by Fruit trees growing there in their hedges and fields, ouer and beſides what hee ſpendeth in his houſe, in Cider and Perrie: And that there are ſome perſons, that haue thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie or fortie Hogdſheds in a yeare for Tithe. And further it appeareth, that in moſt Townes of this Kingdome, there haue beene prouident Husbands that haue planted Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, which in effect are now decayed, which haue not onely beene very beneficiall to themſelues, but alſo to the Commonwealth, and there be yet ſome few that do plant, ſome an Acre of ground, which is yearely worth fiue pound at the leaſt in Fruite. In reſpect whereof and for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good conſiderations, if it were prouided (in regard the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:11304:20"/> like profit may be yearely raiſed in the greater part of this Kingdome, to the great profit of the Planters, and benefit to the Commonwealth, which will likewiſe bee a ſpeciall meanes to disburden vs of the greateſt part of this grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance, for that thereby the extreme price of Victuals will be greatly eaſed,) That there may be a certaine number of fruite trees planted in all the Hedges, as of Apples, War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and Peares, and moſt of all Apples, where White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorne and Crab-trees doe or may hereafter grow being planted, viz. For euery Acre of encloſed ground foure trees, which can no way be hurtfull, or hinder any other profit whatſoeuer that may be raiſed out of hedges. The fruite that by this meanes may be raiſed yearely, can not be leſſe worth then twelue hundred thouſand pounds, if the fruit were ſold but for ſixe pence a buſhell.</p>
               <p>And this I may proue two ſeuerall wayes, Firſt, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience taken from Crabbes, it is knowen to all Huſwiues that a buſhell of Crabbes, will make two gallons and a halfe of Veriuice, and ſo much ſome of the beſt Chandlors in London haue affirmed to mee. I haue alſo inquired of ſome of the better ſort inhabiting in the Countries before recited, as I haue trauelled through thoſe Countries for this purpoſe for my better experience, how much Cider a buſhell of Apples will yeeld, or a buſhell of Peares of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; whoſe anſweres for the moſt part were, that a buſhell of ordinarie Apples, would at the firſt preſſe yeeld two gallons, and a buſhell of Peares for the moſt part, two gallons and a halfe; and by putting a gallon of faire water into the Apples ſo preſſed, and letting it ſtand ſome twelue houres, ſometimes ſtirring them, and then preſſe them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, would yeeld another gallon, but not ſo good for long laſting as the firſt.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:11304:20"/>
               <p>The ſecond is this, that in a buſhell there is about tenne ſcore of the greateſt Pippins, let ſome of them to the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of twentie bee baked in a Pot for the purpoſe, or take twentie of them and roſte, and that man will be holden for a monſter, that can eate ſo many at one meale, which may bee ſold for a penny, and the ſurpluſage being foureſcore, will recompence the labour that is taken about them. By either of theſe meanes I hope it will bee allowed, that of themſelues they are worth the rate before ſet downe, and being baked in Paſte, a good and profitable vſe is made of them in many mens houſes, by ſauing other victuals; and when it pleaſeth God to bleſſe thoſe few fruit trees that are in this Kingdome, it wil ſomething abate the extreme pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of victuals. This preſent yeare may be an inſtance, and all Drouers of Cattell will affirme, that they haue felt the ſmart of the plentie of fruite, and the inhabitants of the Citie of London will acknowledge, that the fruit that commeth thither, eaſeth ſomething the prices of victuals.</p>
               <p>The greateſt hinderance which may be to theſe good workes of planting fruit, and wood, will be confeſſed of moſt men by their experience, who haue in their times ſeene many men beginne to plant orchards, and ſet quick-wood, to the end to haue hedges in many places, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by high wayes for the ſauing of corne; and at the firſt will make ſome prouiſion for the preſeruing of the ſame, which afterwards ſome by coueting the graſſe growing in the orchard, putteth ſome kinde of cattell therein which breaketh and ſpoileth the grafts: others by want of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning the fences, whereby their expectation, coſt and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is loſt, and ſo in quick-wood after a great coſt in plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, for a little more coſt in maintayning, all is troden downe and loſt: in like ſort much good ſpring wood is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:11304:21"/> ſpoiled by cattell by want of good fencing. Thus either by couetouſneſſe, niggardlineſſe, or negligence, many good actions are ouerthrowne to the loſſe both of the owner &amp; common-wealth; my counſell herein is to beginne wel, and to perſeuer therein vnto the end.</p>
               <div type="objections">
                  <head>Obiections againſt planting of fruit.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, that if they bee planted in hedges they will bee ſtolen, and the hedges broken for them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, that ſuch plenty of fruit would make corne ouer-cheape for the Farmour.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, that if the hedges were ſo thicke planted with trees, in cloſes or fields, that are not aboue ſixe acres, they will be very hurtfull; for that if ſuch cloſes or fields ſhall happen to bee ſowen with corne or mowen for hay, the trees will ſo keepe off the Sunne and winde that in wet harueſts it will greatly hinder the drying of hay and corne.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, that his land is his owne, and he will not be conſtrained to vſe it otherwiſe then he liſteth, and that ſuch as haue a thouſand acres or more in occupation, may haue ſo much fruit as he ſhall not know what to doe with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>The anſwere to theſe Obiections.</head>
                  <p>THe firſt I grant in part, that fruit being planted but in particular may be ſtolen, and little good may grow thereby, but being generally planted as is required, what cauſe may any charitable man haue to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine? or what man complaineth in any of the Countries before recited (from whence example for this purpoſe is taken) of ſtealing his fruit, where the hedges are as thicke
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:11304:21"/> with fruit trees and other trees as is required? For ſcarcity cauſeth ſtealing, but in thoſe Countries the trees in the hedges hang as commonly full of fruit on the high waies ſide as on the other, and the hedges of fields and cloſes in thoſe Countries, and in ſome other Countries are as thick of fruit trees and other trees as are required, and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding ſuch as haue corne or hay in little cloſes make ſhift to get it drie. Thus the firſt &amp; third is anſwered.</p>
                  <p>What charity is in the fourth, I referre to the cenſure of the indifferent Reader. For it is in reaſon to be concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that hardly halfe of the people of the Kingdome hath not grounds to plant on, but would buy them at the rate ſet downe, being cheaper then any other victuals, &amp; by the plenty of fruit ſuch ſtore of Cydar may be made and kept without loſſe, vntill it may happen that a deere yeare of corne may come, which then may be ſpent in drinke, and barly be conuerted to bread corne, and by this meanes corne may alwaies be ſold at reaſonable prices in this land. This may bee prooued by the beſt Merchants who will auerre that Cyder will keepe ſeuen yeares. And by this meanes ſuch ſtore of Corne and Cyder may alwayes be in the Realme, that much treaſure may be brought into the land for Corne, Cyder, and many other commodities that may be ſpared, whereby the Kingdome may be great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enriched, and the cuſtomes increaſed to the good of the King.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond is idle: for what man of experience know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not but that the Farmour that liueth by tillage, by fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of beefs, muttons, hogs, pullen, &amp; many other things that may be fed or bred by corne, may make at all times (if hee thinke corne too cheape in the market) by theſe meanes a ſufficient price of his corne for the buyer and ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:11304:22"/> Moreouer, much more ground may be conuerted to the feeding and breeding of cattell and to dayries, all which is (as the world now goeth) very conuenient, the rather for that by experience it hath beene continually ſeene that whereas corne is deare one yeare in ſeauen, yet for other fiue or ſixe yeares it is at a more reaſonable rate then other victuals, which yearely riſe in price, and ſeldome or neuer abate. And further if corne be very cheape it may be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported as it hath beene, with Pery and Cyder into other Countries, ſo that if the Farmours ſhould looſe ſomething in the prices of their corne, yet they ſhall gaine much more in their houſe-keeping and other neceſſaries.</p>
                  <p>And whereas it may ſeeme diſtaſtfull to ſome to plant their Fruit trees in the Hedges; admit that there ſhould be an Acre incloſed, wherein may be planted foureſcore fruit trees, euery tree may haue a eleuen yards roome to grow on, whereby the ground may take no hurt by Woodes, which after ten yeares will yeeld one yeare with another and one tree with another a buſhell of fruit, rated as before at ſixe pence the buſhell, this profit will amount to fortie ſhillings the Acre at that rate. Admit further, that the charge of incloſing of this acre round about, being 8. Rode of breadth, and twentie in length, ſhould coſt 18. pence a Rode, to haue a good Ditch double or treble, ſet with quick Thornes and Hedged round about on the outſide of the Ditch, which Hedge will laſt wel three yeares: at the three yeares end towards the later end of March, cut the quicke wood vpward with a knife cloſe by the ground, &amp; weede the graſſe cleare vp from about the rootes, the wood of the old Hedge will pay for the labour, and then the firſt charge is foure pound and foure ſhilling. Then Hedge it new againe, which may coſt thirtie and ſixe ſhillings, that
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:11304:22"/> Hedge will laſt well till the quicke wood bee paſt taking hurt for that in thoſe three yeares after it is cut, it will grow higher then it would do in ten yeares being not cut, and ſo thick that nothing can get through it. In the meane time whileſt the Fence is in growing, if there bee ſtrewed in a Nurſerie the kernels of a hundred Apples, or kernels of Crabbes, or ſet when or before the quicke wood is ſet, there will be more ſets then that ground requireth, which being well preſerued, will bee big enough in three or foure yeares to graft vpon. The charge being ſixe pound, is but three yeares purchaſe.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="grievances">
               <head>The third and fourth grieuance, For deſtroying of Virmine.</head>
               <p>THe greateſt deuourers of Corne, of theſe kinde are Rookes, Crowes and Sparrowes, the number where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is infinite, and ſo is the quantitie of Corne which they deſtroy yearely. They alſo greatly hinder the increaſe of Corne, which when they cannot find it lying aboue the ground, they ſcratch it vp with their Clawes or picke it vp with their Bils, Blades and Rootes; and when Corne is eared, then if it happen to be laide, both Rookes and Pid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geons light vpon it, and ſo ſpoyle it, that if it were worth fortie ſhillings an Acre before, in one weeke they will make it not worth tenne ſhillings the Acre, One kind of theſe Crowes liue much vpon Chickens and Fowle, and by their Egges, and kill yong Lambes, and doe much hurt beſides. There are alſo many other flying Vermine, that deſtroy Pheſants, Partridges, Fowle, Pullen and young Rabbets, which are Buzards, Kites, Ring-tailes and Pyes, all which or the moſt part of them may eaſily be deſtroyed in three yeares onely, by the pulling downe of their neſts,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:11304:23"/> in breeding time not ſuffering any of them to breed, euery man to vndertake for his owne ground vpon a penaltie, to the vſe of the poore of the Pariſh. Two other great ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Fowle, are the ſhooting in Peeces, and water Dogs; the one galleth more then they kill and get, that are loſt, ſo doth dogges when the Fowle are young, and in moulting time. And much Lead and Poulder might bee ſaued, by reaſon that euery man may haue Hawkes meate by his Fowle and Pullen.</p>
               <div type="objections">
                  <head>OBIECTIONS.</head>
                  <p>THat true it is that is alleadged, that the Vermine before mentioned are as hurtfull to the common wealth as is alleadged, and that many yeares ſince by Act of Parliament there was a ſpecial law made for the generall deſtroying of all kind of vermine that could bee thought vpon, as Foxes, Badgers, Polecats, wilde Cats, Stotes, and all other whatſoeuer, which was as much as then was thought conuenient.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="answer">
                  <head>THE ANSVVER.</head>
                  <p>It appeareth that ſuch an Act was made for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of vermine aforeſaid, and of other vermine, but ſo ſmal an allowance was made that no man made accompt thereof: wherefore by allowing a good propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for this buſineſſe, they may bee ſoone deſtroyed, and the charge ſoone ended; and then all vermine being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed and Pidgeon houſes ſuppreſſed (excepting onely ſuch as are allowed by the Common Lawes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) it cannot be thought that corne will euer be deare.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="crop">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:11304:23"/>
               <head>Of Wood.</head>
               <p>THus it is ſufficiently proued, that wood being ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally planted for euery acre of this Kingdome, being at leaſt foure and twenty millions, the tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber trees growing til they be foureſcore yeres old, cannot be leſſe worth then twenty ſhillings a tree: whereby it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth that euery tree groweth after the rate of three pence <hi>per annum,</hi> &amp; foure trees being planted in euery acre commeth to twelue pence an acre <hi>per annum:</hi> ſo that the ſumme ariſeth to twelue hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> by reaſon that the tenants are but to plant two trees in an acre. And the trees for firewood that are required, togither with the maſt that may grow thereupon, will be as much worth as the timber, and admitting that the fourth part of the Kingdome be already repleniſhed, yet the gaine by wood and timber of the other three parts will ariſe to eighteene hundred thouſand pounds. The timber and firewood that ſhall be planted in paſture ground as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, will be clearely gained by the better breeding and feeding of the number of cattell more that may be bred by the paſture and ſtraw that may be ſaued, which is now ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and burnt, the worth of beaſts two hundred thouſand &amp; twelue <hi>per annum</hi> at the leaſt. All which may be effected with leſſe then three yeares purchaſe in paſture &amp; meadow grounds, &amp; the whole charge of planting in barren ground may be recouered in leſſe then ſixe yeares, &amp; after ten yeares the ſoile will be improued from twelue pence an acre <hi>per annum,</hi> to ten ſhillings an acre <hi>per annum</hi> at the leaſt. The firewood of a thouſand trees being well husbanded wil be worth twelue pence a tree at euery ten yeares end. The
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:11304:24"/> ground is improued ten pound <hi>per annum,</hi> and that the fiue hundred timber trees remaining will be better worth then fiue hundred pounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="crop">
               <head>Of Fruit.</head>
               <p>IT is alſo proued that fruit trees may bee planted in twelue millions of acres at the leaſt in this Kingdome, which being rated at two ſhillings an acre, ſixe pence a tree, the value thereof commeth to twelue hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> out of which being deducted for the fruit already planted in this Kingdome two hundred thouſand pounds, yet there remaineth one million of pounds gained yearelie; and that the fruit trees which ſhall be planted in orchards will not coſt aboue three yeares purchaſe, and in hedge rowes not one yeares purchaſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="birds">
               <head>Of Fowle and Pullen.</head>
               <p>AS concerning the breeding of Fowle and Pullen, it is likewiſe proued that there may be well bred ſo many as will bee worth foure hundred thouſand pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> in this Kingdome, after the rate of eight pence the couple one with another, and that proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion being made for the deſtroying of vermine, there will be Fowles enough ſoone bred in this Realme: and that if euery owner of pidgeons ſhould yearlie breede ſo many Fowles or Pullen, as they keepe old pidgeons, and euery man that hath grounds conuenient would make plots to breede on as is aforeſaid, it would greatly eaſe the dearth of victuals, the charge whereof will not bee aboue three yeares purchaſe: for the better vnderſtanding whereof it is
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:11304:24"/> to be noted that it appeareth by the generall map of this Kingdome that it contayneth nine and twenty millions fiue hundred ſixty eight thouſand acres, out of which num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber deducting fiue millions, and the odde thouſands of acres for high waies, wild lying grounds and waſts not fit for planting, there remaineth foure and twenty millions, which: being rated at a penny an acre amounteth to an hundred thouſand pounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="instructions">
               <head>Suppreſsing of Pidgeon houſes, and deſtroying of Vermine.</head>
               <p>ANd it is likewiſe proued, that by ſuppreſſing halfe the Pidgeon houſes of this Realme, and of Pidge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons kept ouer Gates, Chambers, and other places for that purpoſe, there may bee yearely ſaued ſo much Corne as is worth two Millions of pounds at the leaſt, which they deſtroy and ſpoyle: which may bee effected without charge: and that by the deſtroying of feather'd Fowles, which in like ſort deſtroy and deuoure Corne, and hinder the increaſe of the ſame, there may bee ſaued as much Corne yearely in this Realme, as is worth three mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of pounds. By the deſtroying of the before recited vermine, there may be ſaued in fowles and pullen and egs, which they deſtroy yearely, the worth of fiue thouſand pound at the leaſt, beſides young Fawnes, Lambes, Rab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bets, and many other things by them deſtroyed. I can make proofe where there were within this three yeare ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen douſen couple of Rabbets found on a heape, carried together in leſſe time then a moneth by a Stote. Alſo by a generall deſtroying of Rats and Mice there may be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued yearely in bread, cheeſe, corne and other things
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:11304:25"/> which they deuoure and deſtroy, foure hundred thouſand pound at the leaſt. All or the moſt part of which vermine may be deſtroyed with leſſe coſt then the loſſe which is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained by them in one halfe yeare, by allowing a good proportion to euery man that deſtroyeth them as well young and olde, as their egges and neaſts: which would incourage ſeruants and poore men to be induſtrious, in deſtroying the ſaid vermine, and ſo the worke would ſoone be finiſhed, and the charge ended.</p>
               <p>Summe, nine millions, two hundred thouſand pound ſaued and gained by this proiect yearly to the performers, beſides the good that may grow therby to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</p>
               <p>That it might be prouided that no Tenants ſhould be indamnified by their Land-lords by letting any of their Farmes, whereupon they haue planted wood or fruite, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they haue receiued ſufficient profite of their labour, without ſufficient recompence for their charge.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
